<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon on the occasion of the death of the Right Honourable Elizabeth Lady Cutts containing an account of her most pious life and lamented death.</title>
            <author>Provoste, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2910</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12244584</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12244584</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56889</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56119)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56889)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 875:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon on the occasion of the death of the Right Honourable Elizabeth Lady Cutts containing an account of her most pious life and lamented death.</title>
                  <author>Provoste, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.J. for S. Loundes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In the Savoy [London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Provoste. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cutts, Elizabeth Pickering Cutts, --  Baroness, 1678 or 9-1697.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXVII, 37 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56889:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56889:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON On the Occaſion of <hi>The Death</hi> OF THE <hi>RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE</hi> ELIZABETH <hi>Lady</hi> CUTTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CONTAINING</hi> An Account of her moſt Pious LIFE and Lamented DEATH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOHN PROVOSTE, <hi>A. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Savoy,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. J.</hi> for <hi>S. Lowndes,</hi> over againſt <hi>Exeter-Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56889:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56889:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>JOHN</hi> Lord <hi>CUTTS,</hi> Baron of <hi>Gouran, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have now done the thing which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Your Lordſhip's command for, and I hope that which was a Reaſon to me for the doing it, will be one as much to the World for the accepting it. Indeed there is nothing worthy to he Publiſhed but the Obedience; for however the Work deſerves not to be read, yet Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip does to be obey'd; and ſo whereas the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs is often the Excuſe upon ſuch Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, My Readineſs is to be mine. As the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe has nothing to recommend it but the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, ſo the Publiſhing may have little to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe it but the paying a Duty to one ſo nearly related to the Subject of it; indeed here a Duty is paid to both. It has been always a Maxime to me, that they who ſeem to ſuffer grievous things from Providence were to have all the ſoft Treatment from Men, and were not to ſuffer there again, that from them there ſhould be Balſom and Healing Allay, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be eaſily denied to thoſe in Diſtreſs; and in this of Your Lordſhip the Loſs of the
<pb facs="tcp:56889:3"/>Dead ſhould have at leaſt that faint Supply from the Services of the Living: Therefore was this one of the Melancholy Cries of <hi>Job, Have Pity upon me, have pity upon me, O ye my Friends, for the hand of God hath touched me;</hi> and then follows his Wiſh, very like this Command of Your Lordſhip, <hi>Oh that my Words were now written! Oh that they were Printed in a Book!</hi> But, My Lord, there is yet an higher Reaſon, and that is the Hearty deſire of ſome good to be done, though by ſuch weak hands as mine, upon the Souls of Men, and firſt upon Your Lordſhip's, as you gave the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and ſo the firſt Occaſion for it: There is another right to the firſt Fruits of the Good where the Evil it ſelf began, as we endeavour to quench a Fire at the firſt Houſe which it appeared in: Where this Evil began, it dwells there ſtill in a larger ſhare, and ſo much in the moſt preſſing weight, that there is this new reaſon for its dwelling there, being ſo heavy it cannot eaſily be removed. The Sons of the Patriarch carried a Preſent to the Aegyptian Nobleman of Balm, and that was much uſed by the Aegyptians upon Dead Bodies: But there is another uſe of Balm not only in Death, but in the Wounds before it, and thus I would preſent ſome to Your Lordſhip, ſeeing Peace it ſelf as well as War does expoſe You to them. Your Lordſhip al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſeemed to covet Wounds as much as others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void
<pb facs="tcp:56889:3"/>them, and if there were that Deſire, it has been largely anſwered in all the Coſtly and the Dangerous Honours of War, in all the Painful and terrible Marks of Courage; You have been always ready to ſpare your Conquer'd Enemies, but not Your ſelf, and Your repeated Victories, which You wiſh'd to be dry and unbloody to them, ſeldom were ſo to Your Lordſhip. The Stroke is now in the moſt Senſible Part, and it is now more painful, when through the ſides of another, then when firſt directed againſt Your Self; It was before in other Parts, now in the Heart, and a Pious manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this ſtroke will make it not to be a Fatal one. It is not in the Field of Honour, but of Love, and in the uſual place of ſecurity, in Your own Houſe; as one in the Prophet was ſaid to be <hi>wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the houſe of his Friends.</hi> Death has often met You, when both that and Your Lordſhip were attended by an Army, and it could not conquer You; and therefore it came up to You face to face, and engaged You in a Perſonal Attack, and it has gained its deſign, as the Fortune of Nations has been determined by a ſingle Combat between two Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, when the Diſpute could never be brought to an Iſſue by Armies. Your Lordſhip has born an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Part in two famous Sieges of this Age, at <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Namur;</hi> But You were lately beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Your ſelf within a fair and goodly Town (this the firſt ſurrendered by Your Lordſhip.) You thought
<pb facs="tcp:56889:4"/>Your ſelf ſaſe and happy there, and it had all things within its Walls, but it was not, alas! ſo ſtrong as we could have deſired: Let the Surrender become very Honourable in being very Religious, when Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation is as much the Duty of a Chriſtian as the Keeping of Cities and not reſigning is that of a Soldier. No Order of Men ſeems to ſhine more in Hiſtory, none of the two great Nations, the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian and Roman, are read with more glory to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and more ſatisfaction to us, then Warriours, whoſe Conduct in their Life was equal to that in their Armies, and their Piety to their Courage: Some of that Profeſſion we find upon Record too in the Hiſtory of the Church, and there ſignalized with Marks of Honour greater then thoſe which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the Field. I would not read a Lecture of War to Your Lordſhip, as the Philoſopher did to <hi>Hannibal,</hi> but I would offer things to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the calmer Thought and the ſilent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of Peace, and in the gloomy Shade of Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and I would have ſaid, in the penſive Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure too of Solitude, if that Company, the want whereof, makes this Solitude, would have hindered, would not much rather have promoted the beſt Reflections.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this great Reaſon my Obedience, I frankly own, My Lord, was as ready as if I had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Martial Diſcipline and Authority of Your Lordſhip, as a General Officer. I was no leſs eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:56889:4"/>ordered to the Preſs, then a Soldier is to his Poſt; as one of the Warlike Character, the Centurion in the Goſpel declared, <hi>I ſay to this Man, Go, and he goeth, to another, Do this, and he doth it.</hi> We ſee, there is no Joy unmixt nor without its End, no Expectation ſteady nor without its Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; no hope ſo great, but much rather, becauſe ſo big, it may burſt aſunder, and into that air, which before it ſwell'd with. Your Lordſhip expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Your Return from the Campagne all the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſpoils at home, and things yet more glorious then the Macedonian Conquerors ſeized in the Perſian Tents, or ever the Germans (under whoſe Eagle you have fought) in the Turkiſh Camp. You deſigned a Triumph within Your own Gates, and You there found a Defeat. We now may learn to confide no more in the Weak and Sickly, and (we find) Dying Enjoyments of the World, to enter no more into cloſe Allyances with Life, and with Goods of an Earthly Growth, and we may reſolve that we will no more be Diſappointed. We ſee again, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſays, <hi>There is no Diſcharge in that War,</hi> the Beſt are to die as well as others, and we now live only to be warned and to take the warning, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that we are determined to death by God's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and we ſhould be fitted for it by our Holineſs; and ſo our Death, like that of the Beſt, may ſeem to be only a Debt of Nature, the Payment whereof makes us Free and Eaſie, and a ſudden one, which
<pb facs="tcp:56889:5"/>is to them a Favour, may not be to us a Puniſhment. I would not, My Lord, ſo much condole Your Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, as congratulate Your Improvement of it: I would not ſpeak ſo much to Your Lordſhip upon the Loſs, becauſe (inſtead of Your being <hi>ſwallow'd up,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Phraſe, with intemperate Grief) I would have that ſwallow'd up the beſt way, and ſunk in the Advantage, by the Bleſſing of him who ſaid, <hi>I will heal him, I will lead him, and will reſtore comforts to him and to his Mourners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time I am to tell the World Your Loſs (which Your Lordſhip is too ſenſible of to want the being told of it Your ſelf) and my own Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in the following Pages, wherein the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Lady has her ſelf a Loſs, and, as you were always Partners in the Goods and Evils of Life, Your Lordſhip too ſuffers here, not only by the Death, but by the Deſcription of it in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy and Artleſs Diſcourſe: For all the Injuries whereof Pardon now it ask'd from Your Lordſhip, and from that truly Pious Memory, which now we Celebrate, by</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's Moſt Obedient and Moſt Humble Servant, <hi>JOHN PROVOSTE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56889:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON On the DEATH of the <hi>RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE</hi> ELIZABETH <hi>Lady</hi> CUTTS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 37.37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Mark the perfect Man, and behold the upright, for the end of that Man is Peace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis <hi>Pſalm</hi> and the 73d. ſpeak more together in one continued Diſcourſe than any other part of Scripture upon that great and lofty Subject, The Juſtice of Providence in the Sufferings of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and the Goodneſs of it in the advantages of their better Condition, which follows and Crowns their Sufferings. The end is indeed a full ſatisfaction for all the hardſhips, this a large reward to him who bears them, this a deciſive Anſwer to the Queſtions riſing from
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56889:6"/>them: And ſo God's Providence will not ſuffer in our Thoughts, when the Righteous do from his Hands; the Goodneſs explains the Juſtice, and the Event enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens the Myſtery, that which is ſo bright ſpreads a Light over this which is ſo gloomy. The Honourable, the Pious, and I had almoſt ſaid, the never too much lamented Perſon, of whom every thing around us here does give us mournful notices, for whom we now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form much more than a Ceremony of Mourning, had Peace for her End, and not a train of Sufferings to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct her to it: we alone now ſeem to ſuffer, and more in the end of her Life, than in the misfortunes of our own, and O let all our Evils become the Sufferings of the Righteous, when they are ours. Indeed ſhe was Righteous without them, as if there had been no place for ſeverer methods upon a Spirit ſo gentle in its Frame, and ſo good in its Inclination; and thus a Father does never uſe the Diſcipline of Force upon the ingenuous and willing Child, where he cannot be too kind, and where the kindneſs cannot be abuſed. Give me leave to remember her, who muſt not, who cannot be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and who is ſo much rather to be remembred now, when we are performing that Worſhip to God, which ſhe made as much her pleaſure, as God made it her Duty. And ſurely that always Devout and now Bleſſed Soul (if I may ſo ſay) would at this time ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten in all the ſwifteſt Motions of a Spirit, would come down preſently to joyn in Worſhip with us, were ſhe not engaged already in another Communion with them, <hi>who fall down before him that ſits on the Throne, and worſhip him who liveth for ever and ever,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>and caſt their Crowns before the Throne, ſaying, Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive Glory, and Honour, and Power.</hi> I would ſet before you an Image of her, or a part of that Image, for it can only be a part at laſt: where the Work is not skilful,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56889:6"/>yet the Figure muſt be comely, (or it can have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to her) and then it is ſuch as ſhould only pleaſe and charm, not fright and diſturb you. So much I ſhall ſpeak upon Conviction, that whereas a Pagan might ſay, he had built a Temple, and offered a Sacrifice to Virtue, a Chriſtian may Declare, that he thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to erect a Statue, or build a Monument to it, if there were ſo far a Death of it among us, as to want a Monument, or if any thing I can do could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the being called its Statue. The Integrity of the Speaker, upon ſuch occaſions, is aſſerted by the choice of the Subject, where this ſurmounts the praiſe, as high as it ſeems to be, and ſtill as it riſes higher, this appears much above it; and again, by the knowledge of thoſe to whom we ſpeak, as you think it almoſt your misfortune that once you knew, and perhaps too well, and too much, but not too long: The Veracity is yet more ſecured by the knowledge of him that ſpeaks; as I had the honour to know from Childhood; and now to have the large and delightful proſpect before my Eyes, of ſuch a Glorious courſe of Goodneſs, I could wiſh as much the recalling of her paſt Years, as ſome do that of their own.</p>
            <p>It has been always a part of my Caution, to ſpeak little, ſeldom any thing, of the Dead, in Funeral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes; and as they, according to <hi>David, Praiſe not the Lord,</hi> ſo I have thought, they were ſcarce to be praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves, and we were rather to be ſilent upon thoſe, who (as he at the ſame time ſays) <hi>Go down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſilence.</hi> But ſtill I diſtinguiſht, and it was always no leſs my Rule, that Men, eminent in Quality, and more in good Actions, were not to go out of the World, without ſomething like that ſplendor they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in there, and that ſpeaking then, in Juſtice to them, and for encouragement to others of the ſame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56889:7"/>exalted Rank, and for Example to All, was one part of the needful Decencies of their Funeral. And this, which was ever my Rule, I think, I have a Lawful and a great occaſion for the Practice of. I know the Diſadvantages to which theſe Praiſes are liable in the preſent opinion of Mankind, and therefore my firſt buſineſs ſhall be this, to defend them whenever there is ſo much reaſon as I am ſure now I have.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conſider theſe Three things in my Diſcourſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That we are to mark and behold the Perfect and Upright in this Senſe, when they die in the Lord we are to remember them in their Works which follow them.</item>
               <item>2. That we now have one Perfect and Upright to mark thus and to behold.</item>
               <item>3. That her End was Peace.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. That we are to Mark and Behold the Perfect and Upright in this Senſe, When they die we are to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them in their Works which follow them. Theſe at the ſame time follow them, and are not gone from us, not in their Effects, and ſo not in our Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and the Men who performed them are ſtill to live, not only in their own Souls, but in ours, in all the grateful Thoughts, and all the tender Paſſions thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> (though none of the Beſt of Men) and <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> when Dead, had Praiſe from <hi>David</hi> in a Funeral Song; and however the Friendſhip with one of them might engage it for the Son, the Kindneſs of the other to <hi>David</hi> did not claim it for the Father, and yet he gave it; and the giving it was indeed ſo Great and Generous, that the Praiſe of <hi>Saul</hi> became his own, when the Hatred of this Prince had been as <hi>wonderful,</hi> as he declared,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 1.26.</note> the Love of <hi>Jonathan</hi> had been to him,</p>
            <p>He who had nothing like Vanity or Flattery in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and was far from encouraging either in Mankind,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56889:7"/>ſaid, <hi>Whereſoever this Goſpel ſhall be Preached, in the whole World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.13.</note> 
               <hi>there ſhall alſo this that this Wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n hath don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, be told for a Memorial of her.</hi> And ſhould this Holy Perſon have nothing told? Muſt ſhe want her <hi>Memorial,</hi> when if ſhe had ſeen her Redeemer upon Earth, as ſhe now does in Heaven, ſhe too would have <hi>brought her Box of precious Ointment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 7.38, 47.</note> 
               <hi>would have ſtood at his Feet behind him weeping, would have waſh'd them with her tears, wiped them with the hairs of her Head, would have kiſſed them, and anointed them?</hi> But now alas! we only are to bring our Ointment, that of the ſmootheſt and ſofteſt praiſe, to her Burial, as <hi>Mary</hi> did hers to Chriſt's, <hi>And this good name is better than precious Ointment;</hi> ſhe had not the evil Spirits of <hi>Mary,</hi> nor yet her ſins; to her ſo <hi>much was not forgiven, and yet ſhe loved much.</hi> The Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> writes a Chapter of praiſe upon the Elders, who <hi>dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Faith,</hi> and as he there ſays more than once, <hi>obtained through it a good report, who were ſtoned, were ſawn aſunder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 11.13, 35, 37.</note> 
               <hi>were ſlain with the Sword, not accepting Deliverance, that they might obtain a better Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now what <hi>Dav d</hi> did for <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> What this Author did for the Elders, and moreover, What <hi>Jeremiah</hi> did, and the whole Jewiſh Church for <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.25, 26. we may do for others. What St. <hi>Peter</hi> allowed the weeping Widows to do for <hi>Dorcas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts</hi> 9.36.</note> 
               <hi>a woman full of good Works,</hi> we may do for this other, who was ſo like her, <hi>they ſhewed the Coats and the Garments which Dorcas had made;</hi> we may ſhew the Good Works which ſhe has performed, and we have only this new Cauſe of Sorrow, that here is not, as there was, one Saint to raiſe another from the Dead. You may perhaps expect that before I enter upon this Subject, I ſhould do right to another, that of my Text, that of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which was ſo much her Subject, her great Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, her great Delight. But I cannot ſpeak too little of my Text, in the general Deſign, becauſe I cannot ſpeak too much of her in the particular Accompliſhments, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56889:8"/>claims as large a ſhare in our Grief, as my Text at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time would demand in our Diſcourſe: I can ſcarce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin too ſoon, and when I have begun, I can ſcarce end too late; I ſpeak of her, and of my Text, of both in one, for ſhe Confirms and Improves it, ſhe Illuſtrates and Explains it.</p>
            <p>This will appear in the Second thing, That we have now One Perfect and Upright to mark thus, and to behold. Surely ſhe was moſt Perfect, ſurely ſhe was moſt Upright, and this is our only trouble, that we cannot now behold, in the ſame manner, as we did, the Upright: As for her being Perfect, may I now attempt to prove the thing whereof ſhe gave before much better proof in her Actions, as 'tis ſaid of Wiſdom, that <hi>ſhe ſhall praiſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſelf, and glory in the midſt of her people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 24.11.</note> 
               <hi>in the Congregation of the moſt High, ſhe ſhall open her mouth, and triumph before his power!</hi> I cannot chuſe but deſcribe thoſe Virtues now, which we admired be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſome of the many Virtues which ſhined in her, and which have left ſuch a Light behind them, however ſhe is not, alas ſhe is not here; as the Sun under a Cloud leaves a Day-light to us, though he himſelf is not ſeen. If <hi>the adorning of Women is not to be that outward adorning of plaiting the hair,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 4.</note> 
               <hi>and of wearing of gold, or of putting on of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, but it is to be the hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God of great price,</hi> then certainly none was better dreſt, none more gaudily adorned than ſhe was; and <hi>after this manner,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Peter, in the old time the old Women alſo who truſted in God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 5.</note> 
               <hi>adorned themſelves.</hi> Severe ſhe was to none but to her ſelf, her Actions were directed by a continual and awful Care, and only that ſhe might accuſe her ſelf, for ſurely none beſides was apt, or had reaſon to accuſe her. A Meekneſs ſhe had to bear any Evil, but that of Sin, and any Loſs, but that of Time; and ſhe who had a Fountain of overflowing ſatisfaction within her, was only thus diſſatisfied. Her Dreſſing was one of thoſe things which, as the Philoſopher adviſed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56889:8"/>were not to be done in earneſt, not to be made a Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; it was in this Senſe moſt careleſs, and the careleſs Dreſs was never more comely, ſo every one thought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides her ſelf. Her time of Dreſſing was little, by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and as little as it was it muſt not be loſt, for ſhe thought Time a greater Jewel than any of thoſe which are ſeen upon her Sex, and ſuch of which the leaſt grain is to be preſerved: That there might be the moſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful improvement of it, that (as we read of the Great Men of former Ages) ſhe might do more things toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet every thing as well as if ſhe did but one; in thoſe eaſier Minutes (for that part of her Time was no more) ſhe gave the beſt Inſtructions for the beſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to thoſe about her. Whereas <hi>Caeſar,</hi> with his large capacious Soul, did at the ſame time dictate ſeveral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which were to be ſent into ſeveral parts of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and of the World, ſhe in the midſt of her other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes dictated her Maxims of Virtue to thoſe within her Empire, who therefore only were Subjects to her Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that they might be happy in her Care. May we not ſay of her, as the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> did of <hi>Solomon, Happy were thoſe thy Servants, who ſtood continually before thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>and heard thy Wiſdom?</hi> Her Counſel was ſuch, that one would almoſt deſire to want it no leſs than ſhe did to give it, as ſome kinds of Phyſick are ſo agreeable, that we could be willing to have a pretence for uſing them. Her Reproofs were as ſoft as the Praiſes of others, they were not like thoſe which are ſaid <hi>not to be com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 20.1.</note> but were ſo prudent in the manner, and ſo wholſome in the ends, that one would do any thing but commit a fault in order to the having a title to them: Her Reproofs were ſuch, we might rather wiſh than fear them, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Let the righteous ſmite me, it ſhall be a kindneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 141.5.</note> 
               <hi>and let him reprove me, it ſhall be an excellent Oil, which ſhall not break my head.</hi> Thus in an higher Senſe than <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whoſe Excellence was yet ſo great, <hi>She gave meat to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56889:9"/>her Houſhold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.15, 26.</note> 
               <hi>and a portion to her Maidens, ſhe opened her mouth with wiſdom, and in her tongue was the law of kindneſs.</hi> Her Appointments of Prayer were as fixt as they were Devout, and thoſe evil Spirits of the World, which too often diſturb the Holy performance, made no breach upon them, not Buſineſs, for this ſhe eſteemed ſtill a greater, not Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for in her Thoughts none was equal to this, not Company, for this gave her the beſt and the nobleſt, <hi>The general Aſſembly of the Firſt Born,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 32, 23.</note> 
               <hi>the innumerable company of Angels, and the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect.</hi> The Tidé returns nor with a more certain courſe and a fiercer ſtream, than her Devotions did; and theſe we may ſuppoſe had their Waters too, their Tears, which, like her Money, flowed abroad in Charity; when ſhe had leſs occaſion for them her ſelf, ſhe disburſt them upon the neceſſities, and for the ſins of others. Her Affections were ſwifter than the Hours, were always more then ready to meet the Hours of Prayer, and they met them with Joy, when they came, as they waited for them with eagerneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſhe was only then impatient. In the praying Seaſons what Tranſports, what Elevations and Flights of Soul there were, who can deſcribe? What Violence did ſhe uſe, who was not acquainted with any other, and ſo ſhe took the Kingdom of Heaven by Force? How Divine the Thoughts, How warm the Deſires, How enlarged the Hopes, How lively the Aſſurances, who can tell, and yet who would not give himſelf that nobler Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to imagine? Can we indeed raiſe our Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons high enough to take any meaſures of the Heighth to which thoſe of the Kneeling Saint then were carry'd? If her Frame of Spirit in the Act of Prayer were not yet more Secret, than her Praying was to that God who ſaw in Secret; if it could be known, and if that Knowledge could be conveyed, by Words, to others, the Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would reclaim the Prophane, and Atheiſm would bow down before it: The Libertines would be Converts to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56889:9"/>her Devotion, as they were Objects of her Pity, and their Sin, of her Abhorrence, ſhe in this Senſe <hi>would heap coals of fire not only upon their head, but their heart,</hi> and in this Senſe <hi>overcome Evil with Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her private Devotion was ſo great; and yet there was more then this. Her ſteady reſorting to Publick Worſhip, (which began in her Childhood) was as Viſible as that to Private was not, and ſeen it was, becauſe it could not be otherwiſe, to very good purpoſe in her Deportment, as an Example to thoſe who would learn to behave themſelves moſt Religiouſly, and a Reproach to thoſe who did not, in the Place where all are to ſhew the faireſt ſide of their Behaviour. With all that Reverence ſhe ſeemed there <hi>to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her head,</hi> as the Apoſtle taught her,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.15.</note> to cover it ſo as not to ſee or think of any Earthly Object, and for the ſame reaſon which he offers, <hi>Becauſe of the Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 10.</note> becauſe of their preſence, whom ſhe had ſo near an alliance to, ſo free a Correſpondence with, a Friendſhip, which as that betwixt Men, was founded upon a likeneſs of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and a Love, which began, as that between Kings and Queens, without Sight. The Preſence of GOD did always ſtrike her with awful Reſentments; and her own, in the time of Worſhip, gave awful Thoughts to others: She had all the Impreſſions of Holy Reverence; and every thing which was to make them, found her a Subject ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be wrought on, the ſtroke was gentle, and the effect of it in an inſtant. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>Even in laughter the Heart is ſorrowful;</hi> Her Heart was in the midſt of it very Wiſe and Thoughtful. Speech and Laughter, whereof the one is ſaid to be the Property of Reaſon, and the other to be the Interpreter of it, were in her the conſidered iſſues of Reaſon, they were things which ſhe would not do out of ſeaſon any where, and ſo were things which ſhe could not do in the Sacred Times and Places: St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Have you not Houſes to eat and drink in,</hi> ſhe was ready to ſay,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.22.</note> Have you not Houſes to diſcourſe and to converſe in, <hi>but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56889:10"/>deſpiſe you the Church of God?</hi> She had not only a Native Modeſty, which was ſo happy as ſcarce to have known the Thing, called Evil, and to ſtartle at the Name, but a moſt Generous one which reſolved not to know it, and then it became more a Virtue, as it was more a Principle, and Nature was advanced by Choice. Others do not with ſo induſtrious a Diſguiſe cover their Vices, as ſhe did her Virtues; ſhe caſt a Veil over them, as ſhe would have done over her Beauty, though, like this, they glittered through that Veil, and ſhe ſeemed almoſt to bluſh, when they did ſo, as if ſhe had been her ſelf ſurprized at and dazled with the Diſcovery, and ſhe had ſcarce truſted her ſelf with the Knowledge of them, and in this reſpect too <hi>Her left hand had not known what her right hand did.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.3.</note> A Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity ſhe had which was as Natural as her Modeſty, and, like that, was improved; ſhe had no Art but to conceal all appearances of Art, and there was indeed little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it, becauſe Nature was perfect in it ſelf, and did not want it, as the Innocence of the firſt State of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind did no more deſire than need a Covering. She who was ſo courteous and eaſie in her Converſation was nice and reſerved only in her Accompliſhments. The Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of her Underſtanding were refined at firſt, and they had a ſecond refinement from Reading and Thought, and (which is more) a true turn and byaſs to Virtue and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; to Virtue which is the Perfection of Knowledge, and to Religion which is the heighth of Virtue. Ready ſhe was to comply with all (as the Wiſeſt and the Beſt always are) and not ready to give Laws to any, but her Conduct, where-ever ſhe came, was a Law, without her giving it as ſuch, and her Practice was a Rule, without preſcribing or impoſing. To her ſelf ſhe gave Laws; and theſe indeed were ſuch, as any one elſe would chuſe to be governed by, ſhe ſeemed to have a formed and ſolemn Deſign of being and of making good: Each look was a Precept, and each action was a Moral Rule to all that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56889:10"/>beheld her, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid, if Truth were in a Body, and could be ſeen, it would invite, and would prevail.</p>
            <p>That there might be more hands then one to finiſh a Piece ſo Perfect, and thoſe of the beſt kind too, there was God's Grace, there was her own well directed Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and there was all the prudent Induſtry of a Pious<note n="*" place="margin">In my great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem for her, and for this Religious Care I name her, the late Lady <hi>Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering</hi> of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi> Prov. <hi>22.6.</hi>
               </note> Grandmother, whoſe Memory is now to continue with hers, as before her Care was always with her; So <hi>the unfeigned Faith</hi> that was in <hi>Timothy dwelt firſt in his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother Lois.</hi> 2 Tim. 1.5.</p>
            <p>Thus was the Child <hi>trained up in the way that ſhe was to go in,</hi> and which, if her Age had been of the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended length as our deſires, when ſhe had been old ſhe would not have departed from. I have been often pleaſed with that ſaying of the Heathen, wherein he prays to his Gods for Bleſſings, for eaſie Earth and fragrant Flowers, and a perpetual Spring upon the Tombs of thoſe who pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a Teacher and a Father upon the ſame rank and levell. What Bleſſings then and Rewards are due, and much more due to thoſe who teach Religion, who have that branch of Education for their Care. No Part of Mankind are more uſeful then they are, and none to be more eſteemed by all the reſt; They ſurely are to have Braſs and Marble, even before they die; They are to have all the Honourable Acknowledgments and Publick Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents from the State. No Nation had ever a more nice Eſteem for the Service of thoſe who performed any to their Country, nor ſhewed it in higher and more nice Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards than the Romans: The Benefactors we ſpeak of deſerve Crowns much better then ſuch as the Romans gave, and deſerve them much more then thoſe to whom they gave them, for they do far greater Service to their Country, and ſo much the rather, becauſe they do the greateſt to their Religion.</p>
            <p>The Regard which we ſhould allow to the Goodneſs of this Saint, and which ſhe would never challenge for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56889:11"/>her own, is not to be the leſs, becauſe there was ſo much Pious Care and Wiſe Inſtruction from the Goodneſs of another, as a Picture does not want its praiſe, though it be not an Original, when it is very like one.</p>
            <p>All that endeavour was returned with Intereſt, was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with all the Care and Wiſdom in her ſelf, as one of our Queens is not ſaid to have had leſs skill, becauſe her Council had ſo much, in the Art of Government, and ſhe in following the Meaſures of their Wiſdom ſhewed her own. There is not leſs value for a Building, becauſe it was the Work of Labour and Art, when a goodly Frame at laſt is raiſed, to deſerve all the coſt. Indeed here was a Receiving, but then there was a fruitful Improving of what was received, as the Servant had no abatements to his reward,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.20.</note> when five Talents were delivered to him and he made them ten.</p>
            <p>That ſhe might be extraordinary in every Capacity, ſhe was like her <hi>Prov.</hi> 12. <hi>a Crown to her Husbvnd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.4.</note> ſhe was one of the Beſt Wives, and ſo of the Beſt Women, for the worth of that Sex is never placed in a better Light, never is more diſplayed, nor is more glorious then in Marriage: Piety and Prudence, agreeable Diſpoſition and Experience qualify any one for the filling that Sphere to great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; She had the three firſt in high degree, and, as for the laſt, her Mind was ſo large and comprehenſive in its out-goings, as to take in all that at a ſingle View, which others reach only by the careful toil and the repeated ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of long Experience The being a good Wife was as eaſie to her, as it was delightful to him who had the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of her being ſuch, it had no labour nor force, no ſtudy nor affectation, for Love of every ſort was Natural to her, firſt Divine, and then each other of the Nobleſt kind. She was as good in that Relation as the two great things, Religion and Affection could make her, and ſuch ſhe coveted to be ſo much rather, becauſe ſhe had read good Wives, as <hi>Sarah, &amp;c.</hi> praiſed in Scripture, and ſhe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56889:11"/>was reſolved to add another to the number, and to be, in St <hi>Peter</hi>'s phraſe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6</note> 
               <hi>a Daughter of Sarah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She ſpoke not evil of others, becauſe ſhe was apt to ſuppoſe them as good as ſhe wiſh'd them to be, and if they were not, ſhe thought her evil ſpeaking would not make them good, nor her ſelf the better. If her deſires could have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, there ſhould have been no ſuch thing as Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the World: But ſeeing there would be ſuch a Thing, and that over-grown Monſter would live in ſpite of Virtue, and in defiance to it, whatever ſhe wiſh'd, and whatever ſhe was, reprove ſhe would, but ſhe would not cenſure, not miſpend or carry off any part of that Zeal in a fruitleſs Chaſe and falſe Purſuit of the Perſons, which ſhould have been directed all againſt the Vices. She was ſo little acquainted with Vice, that the Stranger ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed muſt be very diſagreeable to her, when it came into her preſence, and it came without asking her leave, who would not eaſily have granted it: She ſaw it ſo ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom at home, ſhe could not be reconciled to it abroad, the ill-look'd as well as unuſual Figure muſt Surprize and Fright her when ſhe was forced to ſee it.</p>
            <p>She paid a moſt high Regard, as to all Holy things, ſo to Holy times, and her Charity was contented to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der only that others ſeemed not to do ſo, ſhe rejoyced in the approach of the Lord's-Day, becauſe God's Worſhip was the whole Buſineſs of it, which ſhe wiſh'd to be the only Buſineſs of every other day: She rejoyced at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of that Feaſt, which the remembrance of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has a part in, as in the Creation it ſelf,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 38 7.</note> 
               <hi>The Morning Stars ſang together, and all the Sons of God ſhout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d for joy.</hi> She did not chuſe to make Viſits, nor covet to receive them on that Day, and ſhe who was obliging to all ſeemed on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this reſpect leſs kind to her Friends, that they muſt live one Day in the Week without her Company, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it any where but in the Place of Religious Communion: She would thus teach Religion, by the gentle conveyance
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56889:12"/>of a ſilent Inſinuation, or as ſome do Language, by Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and in this as well as every other Senſe ſhe <hi>would do to others as ſhe would have them do to her.</hi> There was all the Diligence in Worſhip, but no Rigour, none there was in that, as none in any thing, it had been a Penance and mortifying Hardſhip only to have forborn it, and not to have deny'd her ſelf any thing for that had been the only Self-denial: Her reſorting to Publick as well as her retiring to Private Worſhip was not as to a Task, but a Diverſion, and it was at the ſame time to do right to her Maker in the Homage, and to her ſelf in the Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>She had not only a juſt and a cool Eſteem, but a paſſion for Goodneſs in all Perſons but one, and all the World beſides had as great a regard for it in that one. She was too buſie in advancing the perfections of others, to be at leiſure for the conſidering her own, as ſome behold ſo much the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of others, that they forget thoſe in themſelves. Her own Accompliſhments ſhe made leſs, and ſo little, that ſhe ſcarce could ſee them, as ſometimes the Object is ſo near, that therefore it is not ſeen; thoſe of others ſhe made greater, Firſt, by her generous Charity, in her high Opinion of them, and then by her Zeal in all the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Advice and Improvement. Her Charity did not begin at home, and it was ſo much abroad, and went out ſo far, that it ſcarce knew its way home, or ever came back again. Her worth was ſeen as a Jewel in the dark; and like other darkneſs, that which ſhe ſought made the thing more awful, as the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Princes raiſe a Veneration to themſelves, in the Thoughts of their Subjects, by the not appearing often in their view.</p>
            <p>Every thing within was, like maſſy Gold, of the moſt Firm and Solid, as well as the moſt Bright and Glorious Subſtance; and ſo the Queen is ſaid to <hi>ſtand on the King's right hand in Gold of Ophir, Pſal.</hi> 45.9. Vanity ſeemed to be ſomething which could not come near, much leſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56889:12"/>into, or have any room in her Breaſt, for this was fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led already with the nobleſt Images, with ſuch as that could not furniſh out in its wandring about the World, nor upon its return bring in with it. She could not dwell upon Shadows, but in a free unbounded courſe muſt go on to Subſtances; ſhe could not live upon Appearances, but would be ſatisfied only with things themſelves, and theſe choſen too with the beſt skill, and the beſt of theſe. Her Mind was too ſteady to be deceived by Words, in her judgment upon this preſent State, as ſhe was too ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere to deceive or impoſe on Perſons; and it was not, like the little Underſtandings, to be abuſed with Names. She was not to be laid aſleep, like Children, with Sounds, nor to be pleaſed with Trifles, and things gay and worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as they are, and are appeaſed by them, when un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet; Her Mind was unquiet with them, only then, if ever, reſtleſs.</p>
            <p>Her Nature almoſt fixed her in her being good, as that of a Star determines it to ſhine, and ſo ſhe would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to foreſtall the State ſhe now poſſeſſes, that of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify'd Spirits, who (though once Angels fell) are at the ſame time Holy by a Choice, and almoſt by a Neceſſity, the Choice moſt joyful, and the Neceſſity a moſt happy one. When the Hiſtorian ſpeaks of his <hi>Roman,</hi> whom he ſeems to be tranſported with the thought of, and would have others to be tranſported too, whom he would ſet up for a Pattern of Honour and Probity, and deſcribe for a Maſter-piece of all the worthieſt and the greateſt things, he tells us that he was good, as for many other Reaſons, ſo for this, that he could not be otherwiſe: And ſo the Original Conſtitution of her Soul was good, and then every thing afterwards muſt be ſuch, as when that of the Body is ſound, every thing muſt be healthful. Her Soul was none of thoſe in <hi>Plato</hi>'s Philoſophy, which had offended in a former State, but it was one of them which reſolve to offend as little as may be in this. The Bow was always
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56889:13"/>bent, in Religious things, but never ſo as to break, and the Arrows that went out from it ſeldom failed to reach their Mark, the Glory of Him who intended and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied her for the promoting of it.</p>
            <p>With all her Quickneſs of Apprehenſion, and all her Tenderneſs of Impreſſions as to other things, ſhe ſeemed very inſenſible to Splendour and Shew, to Greatneſs and Pleaſure; Splendour was ſo far from dazling her Eyes, that ſhe ſcarce ſaw it, or took notice of it, and too Great ſhe was in her Mind, to value the being Great in Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. When others ſcorn things below them, ſhe placed her diſdain upon the higheſt things, and ſcorned nothing upon Earth but that part of it which others are ſo much in love with. The World which is ſaid to have been made for all Mankind ſeemed to be ſomething not made for her, and therefore only not for her, becauſe when ſhe deſerved the beſt things it had to give, ſhe at the ſame time aſpired to better things then ſhe here could find. She lived in a Region far above the Pleaſures of the World, too far to be touched by them, or affected by any influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from them, they did not move her but when ſhe ſaw others too much moved, too eager admirers of them: Or ſhe only look'd upon them, as Spectators do on ſomething which appears extraordinary, they ſtand by unconcerned themſelves, and bear no part in the Show. Her Humility all who ſaw her could not chuſe but know, and all who knew could not chuſe but admire. And would not any one have coveted for a time a mean Appearance, that he might give the occaſion for the exerciſe of her greater Humility, and might have the Satisfaction of its being exerciſed upon himſelf? Would not any one almoſt be the the loweſt Perſon in Condition, when ſhe ſeemed to counterfeit the being ſo in the loweſt Condeſcenſion, who affected or pretended to be nothing elſe ſhe was not? All the while her Greatneſs was ſeen through her Humility, and ſhe had new advantage from the Diſguiſe it ſelf, if
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56889:13"/>ſhe could have wanted any, as the Roman who refuſed the Statue had much more honour then thoſe who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted it. It was ſaid of ſome Emperors, that they would then only have deſerved the Empire, if they had never poſſeſs'd it, ſo much better they were before then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: If ſhe had never been great, ſhe would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be ſo upon a better Reaſon, becauſe ſhe once was great to very good purpoſe, and the after-act was ſo far from debaſing, that it enhanced the Merit.</p>
            <p>She ruled her Family, as <hi>Deborah</hi> governed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and with a Juſtice and a Wiſdom like to hers. Was ſhe not truly a Siſter to the Virtuous Woman, of whom <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid, <hi>Who can find her?</hi> We may ſay, we have found her;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.10.14.27, 28.</note> and we hope we may not ſay, we have loſt her again, when there are ſo many like her; ſome by whoſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhe was made ſo good, and others made ſuch by her own. <hi>Her price was far above rubies, ſhe was like the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhips</hi> (that are laden with Treaſure) <hi>ſhe looked well to the ways of her Houſhold,</hi> and O that ſhe had reach'd the latter Part of the Deſcription, as ſhe went beyond it in the other Parts, that <hi>her Children had riſen up,</hi> and (as every one beſides always did) <hi>had call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d her bleſſed!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her praying had an influence of Piety on thoſe who knew it, and another of advantage on thoſe who knew it not, that is, all Mankind, ſhe prayed for all; they felt the Virtue, as we often do from good Angels, without being inſtructed from whence it came: And thus, as in other reſpects, ſhe loved to ſurpriſe the World, to do good, without being named or declared to do it. We may ſtill hope for continued and new advantages from her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Devotions, from thoſe on Earth, though we expect not any known and particular and expreſs Benefit from thoſe in Heaven; as many hundred years after the Death of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and of <hi>David,</hi> God for their ſakes was kind to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> He loved, and He forgave. When ſhe was not ſeen by others, ſhe was uſeful to them
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56889:14"/>in her Prayers; when they ſaw her, ſhe was ſo in her actions; for would not others chuſe to put on the Garb which they ſaw ſhe wore, and which appeared ſo grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful upon her, and ſo ſhe would turn the Virtue into a Faſhion? They had often met with Temptations to Evil, and too often gone along with them when they met them: But now the allurement and the inviting part is placed on the better ſide, becauſe they had this new Argument for their being good, that, till they were ſo, they were not fitted for her Company, which was as well a Delight as an Honour to thoſe ſhe gave it to, and was as much their Intereſt to covet, as it would be their Pleaſure to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy. Every thing but Vice had the beſt treatment from her, and Vice had the beſt which Virtue could allow it, which her Zeal for Reformation could give it, and which her Prudence could think neceſſary for her to pay, and for that to receive. It was always a Force upon her, not to appear obliging; It was another, to be ſo to any thing which was not Innocent and like her ſelf, unleſs when ſhe had that delight, which was to her a great one, the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and the Hope of making it what it was not; and then this latter Force was leſs then the other, becauſe here the Good was greater then the Evil, the Delight ſhe was careſſed with, then the Violence which ſhe ſuffered.</p>
            <p>All her Merit, as deſcribed before, and all her Conduct in her Family, and every where, could be unknown to few, but were more within the Knowledge of, and had a juſt Value from the Maſter of that Family, as the Heavenly Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies have an influence upon thoſe on Earth at the greateſt Diſtance; but only they who live nearer to the Heat have the more peculiar effects in Fruits and Jewels, and all the Glories of Wealth and Pleaſure. Her Lord was ready to reſign to her the Government of the Houſe, not only as the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> King did that of his People to his Queen, for three days, but for ever; the Length of the Government would have enlarged his ſatisfaction in reſigning it, if it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56889:14"/>could have been as long as it would have been Wiſe and Good. He ſaw with Pleaſure the ſeveral Wheels of his Affairs going round in their true, and calm, and regular Motion, and with ſo much more pleaſure, becauſe he ſaw the goodly Hand which touched thoſe Wheels and moved them. <hi>The Heart of her Husband,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.11.</note> 
               <hi>does ſafely truſt in her;</hi> His Heart not only had a Reliance placed upon her prudent Faithfulneſs, but its paſſions of the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort upon all her Perfections: Theſe were by him daily ſeen, and not made cheap upon their being ſo, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd becauſe familiar; indeed the value for them could not be the leſs, when new treaſures daily were diſcovered. But I muſt not pretend to draw all thoſe kinder motions of Soul, and all the ſofter Inclinations of two united Minds, if they may be called two, in the Conjugal State: thrice happy they who have them, few ſo happy as to be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of repreſenting them: They want Language them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for thoſe Paſſions, however their own, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining Lovers complain of the Narrowneſs of Expreſſion, and they have only this Relief, that their Thoughts are almoſt underſtood by one another, and Words are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by Thoughts: Others then may well be contented to want Expreſſion, and to be ſilent, to have the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of beholding what they have not the Faculty of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing.</p>
            <p>A King of <hi>Judah</hi> was <hi>to ſet his houſe in order,</hi> but then he had ſickneſs, and he had a Prophet to give him warning, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, thou ſhalt die, and not live.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.1.</note> Without any warning, but what ſhe had always in her Mind, ſhe had <hi>ſet her houſe in order,</hi> all things to that time were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted, and ſorry we are, the Parallel between this King and her cannot be advanced ſo far, that years ſhould be added to her Life, as there were to his; and there would have been the Prayers and Tears of others for the Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her time, as there were his for the Renewing of his own.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56889:15"/>
            <p>I have now done the thing, which ſhe did her ſelf much better, who had the beſt way of doing every thing, <hi>I have given her of the Fruit of her hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.31.</note> 
               <hi>though her own works praiſed her in the gates,</hi> not only in thoſe of her own Houſe, but in the Gates of the Court and of the City. I would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider Beauty; to do ſo might ſeem a Diſtruſt, as if I had not enough to fill up the Character without it; where it is conſidered, it ſcarce fills up there, it may be thrown in, and yet make no addition, Beauty in one Sex, like Wealth in the other, may be a Convenience, but is no Perfection, it is far from being that Perfection which my Text propoſes to us. I would not here name it otherwiſe then as it ſhewed us what there was within, or as that ſeemed to be a graceful Curtain drawn before it; Thus was <hi>the King's Daughter all glorious within,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 45.13.</note> 
               <hi>and her clothing too, her outſide was of wrought gold.</hi> So much the leſs would I ſpeak of Beauty, becauſe it gives us too moving a Remembrance of her Body, and the Frailty of it, we would forget her Frailty, and remember only our own: I have all this time repreſented her Mind alone, and the Deſcribing of that entertains us with a chearful Scene, for that is an immortal Part, and now it lives more then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. The Picture is languid and pale, the Strokes are Weak, and the Colours faint; this Likeneſs of her Soul too much reſembles the preſent Condition of her Body: Or rather it is not ſo much like her, as ſomething like a Picture of her, and we may have Comfort, if not Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, when we caſt our Eye upon it; as ſome who have been curious to trace up things to their firſt beginnings and original Reaſons, affirm, that Painting was invented to deceive the Grief and the kind Deſires of Men, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Friends and Heroes to us after Death, that they who excelled in Virtue and reigned in the Affections of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, by a delightful Miſtake, may ſeem to be alive, and we to behold them.</p>
            <p>She who is ſo much in our Thoughts, and ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56889:15"/>to be in one of the beſt places there, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (whether ſhe would or no) highly Good in her Life, but ſtill more did ſhe appear ſo at her Death, in her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers left behind her, as the Riches of ſome wealthy Men are diſcovered, when they dye, to be ſo much greater than we did imagine. But alas! how dear bought was this our Knowledge! We could have been contented to have known no more of her Piety than what we ſaw in her Life, when that Piety was ſo great, and that Life ſo valuable. Was there need of her Death, like that of a Martyr, for the propagating of Religion, as once the Blood of the beſt Chriſtians was the ſeed of the Church? Was ſhe to bequeath her Piety to others in Writing, and as it were by Will? Theſe Papers, (like thoſe of a late No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lady, and directed, as a Letter from the other World, to her Lord,) were far more valuable than ſuch as are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten left by the Learned, to amuſe the World afterwards with <hi>Poſth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mous</hi> Books. The reading of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and other parts of Scripture, which was the daily Exerciſe of Primitive Saints, was to her a daily Duty, and the performing of this Duty was the laſt compoſed Action of her Life, as Religion was the firſt thing and the laſt in her Thoughts: And ſo ſhe went forth from her Cloſet, as a Great General goes out from his Tent to Fight, ſhe went forth to begin her encounter with Death, when ſhe firſt had taken not only St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Shield of Faith, and Helmet of Salvation,</hi> but his <hi>Sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God.</hi> How ſuitable were the <hi>Pſalms</hi> for this Day, for this her Great Day of Tryal! As at the time of the Death of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, the Second Leſſon for the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Service was an Hiſtory of the Crucifying of Chriſt, and read before the King; he ask'd the Biſhop, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended him in his laſt Hours, whether he had choſen that too ſuitable Leſſon for that too ſad occaſion; the Biſhop anſwered, It was no choice, but the Day of the Moneth, and the Order of the Liturgy had preſented it. Another
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56889:16"/>Excellent Perſon, and not leſs ſo for being nearly related to that good Prince, whoſe Piety was as great as his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, heard the laſt Sermon upon that Text, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Wherefore ſeeing we alſo are compaſſed ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut with ſo great a Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> &amp;c. That is, of ſuch, whom, as in the Chapter before, <hi>The world was not worthy of, and who all died in Faith, and confeſſed that they were ſtrangers and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims on the Earth.</hi> The Firſt <hi>Pſalm</hi> of the other fatal Day we ſpeak of, the 139th, begins with a lively Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of that which Governed her, that which ſhe ſeemed to think of always in her Actions, God's Preſence in every place, and His Knowledge of every thing; <hi>O Lo d, thou haſt ſearched me, and known me, Thou knoweſt my down-ſitting, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u underſtandeſt my Thoughts afar off, Thou compaſſeſt my path, and my lying down, and art ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with all my ways.</hi> In the ſame <hi>Pſalm</hi> there is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards a praiſing of God for our Birth, as every one beſides her ſelf had cauſe to praiſe God for hers; <hi>I will praiſe thee, for I am fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fully and wonderfully made, My ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance was not hid from thee, when I was made in ſecret, and curiouſly wrought in the loweſt parts of the earth:</hi> And then alas, her Subſtance thus curiouſly formed was ſoon to be diſſolved. In the next <hi>Pſalm,</hi> the 140th. ſhe read theſe words and her condition made them her own, <hi>O God the Lord, the ſtrength of my Salvation, thou haſt cov red my head in the day of Battle;</hi> That was indeed to her the Day of Battle: And, <hi>Surely the ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hteo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſhall give thanks to thy N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, and the up ight ſhall dwell in thy preſence;</hi> Then was ſhe ready to go into, and dwell in the Preſence of God, and to have that new occaſion of giving Thanks unto his Name. In the other <hi>Pſalm,</hi> the 141ſt. ſhe found ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing very grateful, becauſe very agreeable to her own eager Devotion <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd I cry unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, make haſte un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o me,</hi> then would there be need for her crying, and for God's making haſte to her, <hi>Give ear unto my voice wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n I cry un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o thee, let my prayer be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t forth bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re thee as Incenſe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56889:16"/>and the lifting up of my Hands as the Evening Sacrifice:</hi> She never failed to offer that Incenſe, and that Sacrifice too, not only the Evening, but the Morning one. Had ſhe indeed offered ſo much, that ſhe at laſt had nothing left to offer, but her ſelf, and ſo ſhe became her ſelf a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice? An Evening Sacrifice, for then was the Night co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon her, <hi>in which no man can work.</hi> Her Prayer was truly Incenſe, for never was any thing more ſweet, it was made up of the Breathings of her Soul, never had any thing a more Sovereign and Refreſhing Smell; Warm it was, like that burning at the Altars, and as Incenſe, it was diffuſive, and ſpread all around her, in the Virtue of it, this (as the other things ſhe did) was <hi>an odour of a ſweet ſmell, a ſacrifice acceptable, well pleaſing to God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.18.</note> In the ſame <hi>Pſalm,</hi> ſays <hi>David</hi> afterwards, <hi>Our bones lye ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered at the Graves mouth, but mine eyes are unto thee, O God the Lord, in thee is my truſt, leave not my Soul deſtitute:</hi> She was concerned for her Soul, her Body which every one elſe thought worthy of Care, had little from her, and when it was at the Graves Mouth, ſhe would ſcarce have open'd her own, for its deliverance, if ſhe were to have conſidered, as ſhe ſeldom did, her ſelf alone. The Leſſon ſhe read was 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. which thus begins, <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore then we beſeech you, brethren, and exhort you by the Lord Jeſus, that as you have received of us, how you ought to walk, and to pleaſe God, ſo you would abound more and more: v.</hi> 1. She had walked, and had pleaſed God, and ſhe had abounded more and more, but ſhe was not to do ſo any longer here, ſhe was to make her advances in higher Degrees, and with more eaſe and ſecurity, in the ſtate of abundance and infinite Perfection. The latter part of the Chapter ſpeaks of Death, and of Sorrow for it; And was ſhe to <hi>depart in peace,</hi> upon the reading of that Word, as <hi>Simeon</hi> did upon the fulfilling of another? The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then coveted Death, when he had read <hi>Plato</hi>'s Book of the <hi>Immortality of the Soul;</hi> and ſo did the ſuffering Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56889:17"/>the Noble Army of Martyrs, when they had heard God ſpeaking to them from the Scriptures, as in ancient Hiſtory, the Soldiers are ſaid to do upon the encouraging Orations of their Leaders; They dyed upon the ſtrength of God's Word, as they before had acted by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it, and therefore the demanding of their Bible was to them the worſt ſort of perſecution, as the delivering of it was a worſe degree of Apoſtacy, they were ready to ſurrender their neglected Lives, but never would reſign their Sacred Books. The aboveſaid Chapter goes on thus, <hi>But I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren, concerning them who are aſleep, that you ſorrow not, even as others who have no hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She had all the hope for her ſelf, ſhould then others grieve as if they had none? <hi>For if we believe that Jeſus died, and roſe again for us, even ſo them alſo who ſleep in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus will God bring with him,</hi> v. 14. And <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>Wherefore comfort one another with theſe words.</hi> Theſe were the laſt words ſhe read in her beloved Book, that of Scripture, and they were, you hear, words of Comfort, but they were directed to others, ſhe had leſs need of comfort her ſelf then others, and we are to <hi>comfort one another with theſe words.</hi> I would not imagine that, as ſome have thought upon the opening of a Page in <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mer</hi> and <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil,</hi> there were any preſages Divine and Extraordinary in the thing; but there may be intimations of comfort in the Accident, and ſo however there was only Chance, it was at leaſt a good one.</p>
            <p>Thus her End was Peace; Its being ſo, is the Third thing to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>It was this Peace which ſpoke thoſe Words, <hi>Noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng has frighted me, nothing troubles me, I truſt in God, I do, I do,</hi> and theſe words ſpoke again and declared this Peace; <hi>the gracious words which proceeded out of her mouth,</hi> and very few afterwards proceeded out of it, which yet could not ſpeak too many, nor could we be too much hearers of them.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56889:17"/>
            <p>Her End muſt be Peace, when every thing before was ſo, her Life was Peace with her ſelf, in the Innocence and Calmneſs of her Mind, with God, in the Purity and Sincerity of her Actions, with Mankind, in all the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meekneſs of her Behaviour. Peace muſt be the End, where living as She lived was the Buſineſs. So Prudent ſhe was in the Management of the Things of this World, that ſhe had therefore a new Title to the Bliſs of another, as he who ſhews all the Conduct in a Lower Office de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the Advancement to an Higher one.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 16.10, 11.</note> So <hi>He who was faithful in that which is leaſt was to be faithful alſo in much, and the true Riches were committed only to his truſt, who had been faithful in the unrighteous Mammon.</hi> And, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. The mighty Lord of the Family profeſs'd to him who had improved the fewer Talents by the Skill and the Induſtry of the Uſe, <hi>Well done, thou good and faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, thou haſt been faithful over few things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>I will make thee ruler over many things, enter thou into the Joy of thy Lord.</hi> That the Perfect and Upright Perſon for whom we mourn, for whom we cannot indeed do otherwiſe, ſhould keep Accounts ſo even and ſtrict with Men, was in her a Part of Religion as well as of Wiſdom; at the ſame time a lower Reſemblance and a true Effect of her keeping all things even and ſtrict with God in the Impartial Account of her daily Actions: To be Juſt was but a mean Thing to her, whom Sweetneſs of Soul joyned to the Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Religion diſpoſed ſo much to be Charitable; and how much in her the Beſt Principles of Nature and the Higheſt of Religion prevailed, her Charity was an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the Poor are Witneſſes. Her wiſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her Family prepared her for that Heaven, where all things are done in Order, and according to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of true Reaſon and ſteady judgment, and her Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of her ſelf within (that of the Mildeſt Spirit) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared her for the Place above, the Scat of Love and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, Her ſo Pious keeping of the Day, which at this time
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56889:18"/>we keep, for the enjoying of <hi>the Reſt which remains to the people of God,</hi> and for the Celebrating of the Sabbath which ſhe has now begun, and which ſhall never end. Her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Innocent, Unſpotted and White, made her fit to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with <hi>the Elders who are cloathed in white Robes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9</note> with <hi>the Virgins in whoſe mouth is found no guile,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27.</note> and with that <hi>glorious Church which has not ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing.</hi> Her Zeal, her Conſtancy in Worſhip diſpoſed her to be of one Quire with them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.15.</note> 
               <hi>who are before the Throne of God, and ſerve him day and night in his Temple.</hi> As no Prieſt can be more dedicated to God by his Order, then ſhe was by her Inclination, ſo her daily reading of one part of the Office of the Church, and being thus a Prieſt to her ſelf recommended her to a Place with them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>who ſing a new Song, ſaying, Thou haſt made us to our God Kings and Prieſts, and they have every one of them Harps, and golden Vials full of Odours, which are the Prayers of the Saints</hi> I might thus go on, and at the ſame time ſhew, what her Actions were, and what in a natural Courſe they tended to, and that was Heaven,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 5.8.</note> and ſo, in <hi>David</hi>'s Phraſe, <hi>Her way</hi> thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>was made ſtrait before her face:</hi> This attempt may well be a Part of my Undertaking, becauſe I cannot think of a Perſon eminently righteous, when Dead, but I muſt in that inſtant think of Heaven, as when I remember one that is abſent, whom I have great regard for, I cannot but think of the Place which has the Preſence that I want and ſigh for. Indeed Heaven was to be the end of her Actions, which was the Object of her Thoughts, for Actions rife from Thoughts, and then muſt have a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to them, as waters have to the Fountain from whence they flow, and how good muſt her Actions be, which flowed from ſuch Thoughts as thoſe of her Mind always were. She was not to have the Pleaſure of Knowing before that ſhe was to die, it was enough to have that of enjoying afterwards what ſhould follow Death; She muſt not have the Pleaſure, that others might not have the trouble, the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56889:18"/>lengthened pain of the notice, and ſhe was not apt to think her ſelf happy in any thing which others thought trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to themſelves. She was no otherwiſe ſurprized with Death, then as we often are with ſomething Joyful and Great, which is not leſs welcome, becauſe leſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. She was not to leave a Child behind her, in pity to us, that we who had ſo many other occaſions might not have this to bleed anew in our wounds, to remember the Firſt Self in the Second; There was leſs need of any Child from her, who has left Pledges of her ſelf yet more No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, a whole race of multiplied Virtues, and there was more glory to her, that in this as in other reſpects ſhe might be now more <hi>like the Angels of God in Heaven</hi> (where ſhe is) who have no Off-ſpring,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.30.</note> and are Immortal in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without the help of Children to make them ſo. The Writer of the Book of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ſpeaks of a Woman Righteous and Childleſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſ.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>She ſhall have fruit in the Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Souls,</hi> and of ſuch a Man, <hi>To him ſhall be given the ſpecial Gift of Faith, and an Inheritance in the Temple of the Lord more acceptable to his Mind, for glorious is the Fruit of good labours, and the Root of Wiſdom ſhall never fall away. Better it is to have no Children, and to have Virtue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſ.</hi> 4.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>for the memorial thereof is immortal, becauſe it is known with God and with Men; when it is preſent, men take example from it, and when it is gone they deſire it, it weareth a Crown, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umpheth for ever, having gotten the victory, ſtriving for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled rewards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The private Peace, which was at all times within her Breaſt, was lately ſo much more, becauſe there was a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick one; that ſhe at her Death, as the Angels at Chriſt's Birth, ſhe at her going up to Heaven, as they at their coming down from thence, might <hi>praiſe God, and ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Glory to God in the Higheſt, and in Earth Peace, Good will towards men.</hi> But was ſhe to be offered upon the return from War, as the Daughter of <hi>Jephthah</hi> was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 11.31.38.40</note> 
               <hi>the mighty Man of valour,</hi> who had declared, <hi>Whatſoever cometh forth of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56889:19"/>the Doors of my houſe to meet me, when I return in Peace from the Children of Ammon, ſhall ſurely be the Lords?</hi> She offered her ſelf to God, when Living; muſt ſhe, when Dying, be made an Offering too, like the Lambs and Turtles under the Law? The Daughter of <hi>Jephthah had two Months</hi> allowed her <hi>to bewail</hi> her fate <hi>upon the Mountains,</hi> there were not two Days here: <hi>The Daughters of Iſrael went yearly to lament the Daughters of Jephthah four days in a Year;</hi> the Daughters and the Sons of <hi>Iſrael</hi> lament in the caſe before us, and not four days only, not in an Yearly, but a Daily courſe of Mourning.</p>
            <p>And now perhaps my Hearers will ſay, With all thoſe Perfections, wherein you have pronounced her Perfect and Upright, there was one thing too Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that was her Life, that too ſhort; Young ſhe was, and Young ſhe died, alas as Young as Good; Eighteen Years and Eighteen Days; How narrow a Space for ſomething of ſo Great a Compaſs to be contracted, bound up, and reſtrained to! This ſhould be no more a grieveous thing, then it is, that any one ſhould run a Race in a little time, and win the Prize, when the very running in leſs time does win it; <hi>So run that you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and then you may be concerned no farther, not for your ſelves, not for others. She was the more a Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that ſhe thus ſoon ſhould become thus Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and ſuch Excellence was a particular Mark of God's Favour, as it was the peculiar Gift thereof: She muſt receive it from Him alone, when there was not the uſual courſe of Time and long method of Diſcipline for the attainment of it, as Miracles are not wrought by ſlow, by natural and common ways. Therefore you read,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>to</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſdom</hi> 4 <hi>Though the righteous be prevented with Death, yet ſhall he be in reſt, for Honourable Age is not that which ſtandeth in length of Time, nor that is meaſured by number of Years, but Wiſdom is the Gray Hair unto Men, and unſpotted Life is Old Age,</hi> (And then how Old was ſhe, of whoſe ſhort Life we ſo much complain!) <hi>Yea ſpeedily was Enoch
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56889:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>taken away, leſt wickedneſs ſhould alter his underſtanding, and dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t beguile his Soul, He being made perfect in a ſhort tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, fulfilled a long time, This the people ſaw, and under ſtood it not, neither laid they up this in their Minds, That God's Grace and Mercy is with His Saints, and that he hath reſpect to His choſen. Thus the righteous who is dead ſhall condemn the ungodly who are living, and youth which is ſoon perfected, the many years and old age of the unrighteous; for they ſhall ſee the end of the wiſe, and ſhall not underſtand what God in his Counſel hath decreed for him, and to what end the Lord hath ſet him in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> And Ecclus. 41. <hi>Fear not the ſentence of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 41 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them who h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve been before thee, and who come after, for this is the Sentence of the Lord over all fleſh, And why art tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſt the pleaſure of the moſt High? for there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition in the grave, whether thou haſt lived t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, or an hundred, or a thouſand years.</hi> Indeed <hi>the hoary head is a crown of glory, if it be found in the way of Righteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 31.</note> Prov. 16. But Righteouſneſs at any time is a Crown of Glory, it is to the head which is not hoary, ſo much more to this, when the Righteouſneſs has not, like that of Old Age, the ſins of Youth to deface it, not the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of approaching Death to leſſen it, and has only the Graces and Charms of Virtue to recommend it, not the Experiments and Evils of Vice to force it. Here was a Bloom of Age, but then here was a Ripeneſs of the two beſt Fruits which grew in the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> and now in the Wilderneſs of the World, Virtue and Wiſdom, as in ſome hotter Countries a Bloſſom is ſeen upon one part of the Tree, and ripe Fruit upon the other. And ſo in this Sence too, <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Prophecy is fulfilled, <hi>The Child ſhall dye an hundred years old;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.20.</note> and his Queſtion is anſwered, <hi>Who hath heard ſuch a thing,? Who hath ſeen ſuch things?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8.</note> 
               <hi>Shall the earth be made to bring forth in one day, or ſhall a Nation be born at once?</hi> He who in few days made all the World, might well in few years make her that which He would accept, and He would love, and here too, as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56889:20"/>after the Creation, He in a pleaſing Review, <hi>ſaw that which He hid wade,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.41</note> 
               <hi>and behold it was very good.</hi> Gen. 1.12. She had all the Grandeur and comely Gravity of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Matrons, when ſhe had the Youth of their Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, her Age we could much rather have deſired to have been that of the Mothers. How beautiful ſhould we have thought Old Age in her, if we could have ſeen it there! How charming had wrinkles been in her Face, and each deeper Line upon her Cheek had given us a fairer Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect than the moſt fruitful Valleys! We could indeed have wiſht her Life, and when once we had enter'd upon the wiſh, we know not when and where we ſhould have ceaſed, nor how we could have diſengaged our ſelves again from a Thought ſo entertaining; As there is a Great Prince near the Empire of <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> for whom his Subjects have ſo high a Veneration, that they are not willing to believe him Mortal, but pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with an extravagant Notion, that he has been the ſame from many Ages, and will be ſo to many more, and there ſhall be no other Change upon him, than ſuch as follows that of the Moon; in the Full Moon, they ſay, he appears an Old Man, in the New again a Young one in the Publick Temple, and in the view of all his People.</p>
            <p>As there was little Time allowed to her Life, ſo you may think, there was too little to her Death. But then her Death, which may ſeem ſurprizing, was no more an Evil, than that Change ſhall be, the ſudden Change of thoſe who ſhall be living upon Earth when Chriſt comes to Judgment, and who <hi>ſhall be changed in a moment, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> twinkl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng of an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51, 52.</note> 
               <hi>at the laſt Trump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> And, as in that very Chapter, which was the laſt read by her, who had read ſo many, <hi>They who are alive and remain, ſhall be caught up in the Clouds to me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the Lord in the air,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo ſhall they ever be with tin Lord.</hi> Nor is there any Evil ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in being <hi>caught up thus,</hi> and ſnatched away, for St. <hi>Paul</hi> preſently ſays,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore comfort one another with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56889:20"/>theſe words,</hi> and he is willing himſelf to be of the ſame number, and in the ſame condition, he ſpeaks twice as of himſelf, <hi>Then we</hi> (as if he were to be included) <hi>We who are alive,</hi> &amp;c. There is not Anger or Puniſhment,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 15, 17.</note> but Favour and Bleſſing in the Death of the Righteous which has not long Solemnity, and ſo much Ceremony; as Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces often come to tire Houſes of Favourites in a private manner, without Pomp and Train. So <hi>Wiſdom</hi> 4.14. Enoch's <hi>Soul pleaſed the Lord, therefore haſted he to take him away from among the wicked.</hi> Love is eager as well as Wrath, and there is a Kindneſs as well as a Fury, which haſtens, and which does the thing without Delays and Forms. <hi>The Righteous periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, the merciful men are taken away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>none conſidering that the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is taken away from the evil to come</hi> (From the ſnares of Life, from the calamities and from the ſins of the World) <hi>He ſhall enter into peace, they ſhall reſt in their beds.</hi> And can we <hi>enter into peace</hi> too ſoon? Does any one think it a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, that, when he is weary, he ſhould haſten to his Bed? The Prophet calls our Graves by a Name ſo very ſoft as that of Beds; And yet our Notion of them is to out-do that Name, they are yet more ſoft than theſe, for a Bed may have Feaveriſh Nights and raging Pains, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Sleeps and unpleaſant Dreams, but there will be caſe in the Grave, there will be nothing to diſturb it. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I never read the Funeral Service with more paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate reſentments, than over the Tomb, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains of this wonderful Lady; with what Regret did we all leave them behind us, ſeeing every thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides had left us, and there was nothing of her upon Earth but theſe, as the Mantle fell from <hi>Elijah,</hi> when he went up to Heaven by the haſty conveyance of a whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind, and in the glaring pomp of a flaming Chariot? And yet in the ſame Service, and at the ſame time, we gave God hearty Thanks, becauſe it had pleaſed Him to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this our Siſter out of the miſeries of this ſinful World;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56889:21"/>the ſinfulneſs of it was to her the greateſt of its miſeries, that ſeemed to her a Diſeaſe, but it was not a contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous one, ſhe was not infected with the Evil, though ſhe was diſcompoſed upon the view. Our complaining is to be leſs, that ſhe who was always Honoured, and is now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by all, ſhould dye ſo very ſoon, then our Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, that once ſhe lived, as when a new Star is ſeen, and then ſeen no more, the Philoſopher does not repine that it is no longer viſible, but with all the niceſt pleaſure he enquires into the Light and Influence, and Motion, and all the Properries of it, which could be obſerved while it it did appear.</p>
            <p>I want no Warrant from any one for the giving all this Praiſe, I ſhould have wanted Pardon from my ſelf, if I had not given it, and the only evil, I know, is this, that there ſhould be now occaſion, as there was always reaſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.30.</note> for it. Could I have need of a Warrant, <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf has one ready for me, <hi>The woman that feareth the Lord ſhall he praiſed:</hi> And the wiſe Son of <hi>Syrach</hi> has another, when he ſeems to ſummon all thoſe who have any worth of their own, or who love it, and have had any advantage by it in others, to a Conſort of Praiſe; <hi>Let us now praiſe Famous Men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus</hi> 44 12. 34.7, 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord hath wrought great glory by them, through his great power from the beginning, Such as gave counſel by their underſtanding, Were leaders of the people by their Counſels, wiſe and eloquent in their inſtructions, All theſe were honoured in their Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rations, and were the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Times, They have left a Name behind them, that their praiſes might be reported, The people will tell of their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Congregation will ſhew forth their praiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Indeed we are ſafe in the praiſes we give, and others in thoſe they hear, without danger of impoſing on them in the believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and on our ſelves in the Action, when we do not; as the antient Panegyriſts, teach the Perſons praiſed what they ſhould be, but others what they are, and what they themſelves ought to be. The defects of him who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56889:21"/>forms the Office, and in his manner of performing it, ſuppoſe not any defect in nor bring any diſadvantage up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Perſon for whom it is performed, becauſe we are to imagine a greater and more commanding Worth, where the Dignity of the Matter does raiſe the loweſt Genius to the unequal attempt, and where, to give juſt Praiſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, a Man will generouſly forfeit his own, as, to pay a great Debt to another, we ſometimes leave nothing to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Thus died, as you have heard, the Devout and the Good, the Worthy and the Honourable, after a Life <hi>full</hi> of Merit, though not <hi>of Years,</hi> a Life which deſerves far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things then you yet have heard. And how could we ſo much as ſay, ſhe is Dead, much leſs bear the painful Reflection upon her being ſo, if there were not an allay to the thought of the Evil from this manner of it? Did I call it an Evil? If Death be any, may we ſuppoſe it to be that ſo much leſs, ſince ſhe paſs'd through the Iron Gates and all the gloomy Solemnities of it, as where-ever ſhe came ſhe uſed to leave ſomething of advantage to thoſe who ſhould come after her, and every thing was always the better for her? To die ſtanding was the great Roman's deſire; It Would have been hers to have died rather Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not only in her preferring the laſt of her many Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers on Earth to her God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59, 60.</note> as St. <hi>Stephen fell aſleep calling upon God,</hi> but in the loweſt Submiſſion to the Stroke, as her Saviour <hi>bowed his head, and gave up the Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.30.</note> She died (if that be a Thing ſo pleaſant, as to be repeated) and then her Soul went upwards, and took its boundleſs ſlight, not, as that of the Emperor from the Funeral Pile, on the Wings of an Eagle, but on thoſe of Angels: And we may well imagine, <hi>there was joy in Heaven,</hi> when ſhe came,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.5, 7.</note> though, like <hi>the ninety and nine juſt perſons,</hi> ſhe had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leſs <hi>need of repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May we not paſs now from her, who was never before an unpleaſant Subject? And yet why muſt ſhe now begin
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56889:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be ſo? Why ſhould the Subject, when She is named, be Unpleaſant now, ſeeing the Condition which ſhe is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled in, is Glorious for ever? And then ſhould we ſhed our tears over her, and not over our ſelves alone, who are not in the ſame bliſsful State which ſhe in, and yet envy it not to her who wiſhes it to us, to all? As our dying, Lord declared to the relenting Sex,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.28.</note> 
               <hi>Ye Daughters of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves;</hi> He, from whom the Dead have all their Bliſs, and from whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone we are to expect it. That we may be fitted and in a juſt Capacity for it, We will paſs from her to our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Seeing we are to Mark and Behold her as Perfect and Upright, I would by the pleaſing View of this Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Pattern raiſe a Spirit of Piety in others who want it, and raiſe it higher in thoſe who have it; And ſeeing Life, in the Beſt, is a thing ſo uncertain and ſo ſhort, I would have that glorious hope of moving thoſe who are not good to conſider with what hazard they are not, and thoſe who are to remember with what preſent advantage they are ſuch, in their having longer time for all the moſt enlarged improvements. The Lamp which the Philoſopher uſed in his Studies, the effects whereof had been ſo great in his Writings, was purchaſed, after his Death, at the higheſt price: But now there is the ſame Light for others, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Price and Expence, to read and to walk by, which this Holy Perſon uſed to read good Books by in her Cloſet, and to direct all her motions in the World; there is more Light then ſhe had, a new one, for there is that of her Example, and, if they do not uſe it, their guilt is greater, it began to be ſo from the day that they had ſuch an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. this I am unwilling to ſay, for it is a much more pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Office, not only to him to whom it is done, but to him who does it, to congratulate a Reformation, than to reprove a Fault, as it is more delightful to ſee the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very from a danger, than to give notice of it; there is no ſuch matter of Joy in repreſenting the Fault greater by its
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56889:22"/>aggravations, as in the Sinner's making it leſs by his change. When the Jewiſh Writer had bewailed the end of an unhappy and vitious Woman (for ſuch there were among the Jews) he comes at laſt to this practical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, and then directs it to all who ſurvived her, <hi>They who remain ſhall know that there is nothing better than the fear of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 23 27.</note> 
               <hi>and that there is nothing ſweeter than to take heed to the Commandment of the Lord.</hi> May not we make uſe of the ſame Concluſion, and with the ſame Addreſs, but with greater ſatisfaction, becauſe upon the death of one who was the Reverſe of that <hi>careleſs daughter of Zion,</hi> who was ſeverely and bravely good in the midſt of all the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages, indeed, of things which ſeldom have ſo ill a name as that, and ſhould never deſerve it, I mean Youth and Beauty, Wit and Honour, and that Enchanting. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a very wealthy Fortune, which being in our view, does often ſo fill out Eye, that we ſee nothing beſides it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Seeing her End was Peace, ſhall we then bewail it with that exceſs which is to be reſerved for thoſe alone, whoſe End is not ſuch? When her Death was Peace, Shall our Life be otherwiſe? Her End was Peace, and her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition will be ſo for ever: We have joyful Reaſons, in the midſt of all this Grief, for that aſſurance. You have heard the laſt Chapter ſhe read, (Sorry I am, that I muſt call any thing ſhe did, the laſt) and you know the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions thereof: But was ſhe indeed to reſign her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained and lovely Soul, that there might be a preſent want of this Relief to our own, that we might thus (not ſo much at her coſt, as ours) begin the too early executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the advice which that Chapter gives us?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let Peace not only be her End in poſſeſſion, but ours in Reverſion: Let our Life be <hi>perfect and upright,</hi> that our going out of it, may be joyful and aſſured, and that in the mean time our Prayer may be ſo too; And then we may pray (as in the Funeral Office) <hi>that we with all thoſe who are departed in the true Faith of God's Holy Name may
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56889:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>have our perfect conſummation and bliſs, both in body and Soul, in his everlaſting Glory.</hi> Let us all pray, as the once li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Saint always did, moſt devoutly, and (as in the Prayer, which now preſently follows in the Service of the Church) being reconciled at laſt to our Loſs, and bowing down to the black Decrees of Providence, let us, in a change of Language and of Paſſions, <hi>Bleſs God's Holy Name for all his Servants departed this Life in his Faith and Fear, beſeeching Him to give us Grace ſo to follow their good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, that with them we may be partakers of His Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kingdom; Grant this, O Father, for Jeſus Chriſt's ſake our only Mediator and Advocate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the God of Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>who brought again from the Dead our Lord Jeſus, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant, make you perfect in every good Work to do His will, working in you that which is well pleaſing in His ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom (with thee, O Father, and thee, O Holy Ghoſt) be Glory for ever And ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
